<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>
                    NLANJIRBƆR DEFEATS UBƆR IN A BATTLE OF WITS
                </title>
                <author>Konkomba Oral Tradition (Ghana)</author>
                <storyteller>Yaawork</storyteller>
                <editor>Tasun Tidorchibe</editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <name>Tasun Tidorchibe</name>
                    <resp>transcript, editing and translation</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <name>Anna Schmitt</name>
                    <name>Lara Wenisch</name>
                    <name>Hannah Lea Küppers </name>
                    <resp>coding and editing</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <name>Prof. Dr. Eva Ulrike Pirker</name>
                    <resp>supervision</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor type="digitisation">E-Learning Förderfonds HHU</sponsor>
                <sponsor type="funding">Katholischer Akademischer Ausländerdienst</sponsor>
                <address>
                    <name type="institution">Centre for Translation Studies Düsseldorf</name>
                    <name type="institution">Heinrich-Heine-Universität Düsseldorf</name>
                    <street>Universitätsstraße 1</street>
                    <postCode>40225</postCode>
                    <name type="city">Düsseldorf</name>
                    <name type="country">Germany</name>
                </address>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Centre for Translation Studies Düsseldorf</publisher>
                <status>not yet published</status>
                <pubPlace>Düsseldorf</pubPlace>
                <address>
                    <name type="institution">Centre for Translation Studies Düsseldorf</name>
                    <name type="institution">Heinrich-Heine-Universität Düsseldorf</name>
                    <street>Universitätsstraße 1</street>
                    <postCode>40225</postCode>
                    <name type="city">Düsseldorf</name>
                    <name type="country">Germany</name>
                </address>
                <availability>not yet available</availability>
                <date>TBD</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>
                    <title>NLANJIRBƆR DEFEATS UBƆR IN A BATTLE OF WITS</title> <storyteller>
                        Yaawork</storyteller>Translated by<editor role="translator">Tasun Tidorchibe</editor>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <styleDefDecl scheme="css" Version="2.1"> </styleDefDecl>
            <tagsDesc>
            </tagsDesc>
            <editorialDecl>No author can be assigned to the story due to it being an oral tradition;
                The decision was taken to treat notes the same as a glossary in terms of coding</editorialDecl>
            <projectDesc>The project focuses on digitising oral folktales from Ghana, specifically
                the Konkomba people, through different media.
                The project puts a body of oral folktales into writing and eventually makes them
                available as annotated, digitised narratives.
                It thus aims to make a contribution to visibilising this culture, which through
                processes of colonisation, the accompanying priviledging of written/print culture
                and Eurocentric/Western thinking has been marginalised.</projectDesc>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation> Originally told at <place xml:id="Chakping, Saboba">
                    <placeName>Chakping, Saboba</placeName>
                    <location>
                        <geo>9.67, -0.27</geo>
                    </location>
                </place>
                transcribed folktale from Likpakpaln as told by <name type="storyteller">Yaawork </name>
                on <date when="2022">16th March 2022</date> in <name type="city">Chakping, Saboba</name>
                ,<name type="country">Ghana</name>
            </creation>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="lik">Likpakpaln</language>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>placeholder tbd</textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <head type="mainTitle">NLANJIRBƆR DEFEATS UBƆR IN A BATTLE OF WITS</head>
            <p>(as narrated by Yaawork at Chakping, Saboba on 16/03/2022)</p>
            <div type="introduction">
                <head type="subTitle">Introduction</head>
                <p> The following story is a variant of a tale (in the Konkomba folklore) that
                    features a little boy who outsmarts a self-acclaimed wise <term ref="#gloss4">
                    ubɔr</term>. In this variant, a battle of wits ensues between a certain <term
                        ref="#gloss4">ubɔr</term> (i.e., the political head of a Konkomba community)
                    and a little boy when the latter decides to call himself <term ref="#gloss2">
                    Nlanjirbɔr</term> – a name which translates as <q>Wiser than <term ref="#gloss4">
                    ubɔr</term>.</q> In the end, the boy proves to be truly wiser than the <term
                        ref="#gloss4">ubɔr</term> and receives two cattle from the former.
                    Essentially aimed at showing that no man is the repository of all wisdom, this
                    story reflects the Konkomba belief that names have the power to shape behaviour
                    and determine destinies – the reason Konkombas often give names that communicate
                    specific messages or wishes parents desire for their families, their children
                    and even their foes. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="story">
                <head type="subTitle">Story</head>
                <p>
                    <q>There lived a certain <term ref="#gloss4">ubɔr</term>,</q> Yaawork commences
                    her story directly without the usual introductory protocol of declaring her
                    intent to tell the story.<term xml:id="footnote1">
                        <hi rend="superscript">1</hi>
                    </term> She then proceeds
                    as follows: </p>
                <p> One day a child was born in his community. The child told the parents to name
                    him <term ref="#gloss2">Nlanjirbɔr</term>. When <term ref="#gloss4">ubɔr</term>
                    heard it, he wasn’t happy about it – for he couldn’t fathom why a little boy
                    would claim to be wiser than him. <term ref="#gloss4">Ubɔr</term> therefore
                    summoned him and confronted him. But the boy told <term ref="#gloss4">ubɔr</term>
                    to fret not because his title was <term ref="#gloss4">ubɔr</term> while his name
                    was <term ref="#gloss2">Nlanjirbɔr</term> – the two were, thus, not the same. </p>
                <p> A while after this confrontation, <term ref="#gloss4">ubɔr</term> summoned <term
                        ref="#gloss2">Nlanjirbɔr</term> again. When the boy arrived, he took him to
                    his cattle ranch and gave him an <term ref="#gloss3">unaaja</term>. He then told
                    the boy to take the unaa home and look after it so that when it gave birth, they
                    would share the calves. Without uttering a word, the boy took the <term
                        ref="#gloss3">unaaja</term> and departed. </p>
                <p> On arrival he informed his father, who couldn’t help but wonder how and why <term
                        ref="#gloss4">ubɔr</term> could give his son an <term ref="#gloss3">unaaja</term>
                    to take care of it so that when it delivered, they would share the calves. The
                    boy then told his father not to worry because he knew exactly how to make the
                    unaa multiple. </p>
                <p> The next day, at the crack of dawn, the boy took a machete and went to <term
                        ref="#gloss4">ubɔr</term>’s palace. Near the palace was a shea tree. The boy
                    started chopping the tree, kpa kpa. One of <term ref="#gloss4">ubɔr</term>’s
                    wives heard the noise, came out of the house and saw the boy chopping the tree.
                    She then called out to <term ref="#gloss4">ubɔr</term> to come out quickly
                    because <term ref="#gloss2">Nlanjirbɔr</term> was chopping the tree near the
                    palace. <term ref="#gloss4">Ubɔr</term> soon emerged from the house and asked, <q><term
                            ref="#gloss2">Nlanjirbɔr</term>, why are you chopping the tree at this
                    ungodly hour?</q> In reply, the boy told him that his father had given birth the
                    previous night. Unfortunately, they didn’t have firewood to boil water for him;
                    and so, he was chopping the firewood for that purpose. On hearing that, <term
                        ref="#gloss4">ubɔr</term> shook his head, amid laughter, and asked: <q>How
                    on earth can a man give birth?</q> The boy replied, <q>Well, if males don’t give
                    birth, why did you give me an <term ref="#gloss3">unaaja</term> to take care of
                    it so that when it gives birth we’ll share the calves?</q>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <term ref="#gloss4">Ubɔr</term> realised that the boy had outwitted him. He then
                    took the boy to the ranch again and gave him … </p>
                <p>
                    <q>… an unaasal,</q> interjects one of Yaawork’s audience who probably thought
                    that the storyteller had forgotten that detail due to a short pause she made. </p>
                <p>
                    <q>… an unaasal,</q> Yaawork adds that detail and continues her narration as
                    follows: </p>
                <p> The boy took the unaa home and hitched it outside the house. When the father
                    came out of the house, he saw it and asked his son, <q>Ah! ’lanjirbɔr, you
                    brought only one unaa yesterday; how come there are two inaa today?</q> The boy
                    replied, <q>Yesterday I told you I knew how to make the unaa multiply, didn’t I?</q>
                    He then added that at dawn he went and started chopping a tree near <term
                        ref="#gloss4">ubɔr</term>’s palace. The latter came out and inquired why he
                    was doing that, and he told him that his father had given birth the previous
                    night. He added that <term ref="#gloss4">ubɔr</term> then asked him how on earth
                    a man could give birth, whereupon he in turn asked him why he had given him an <term
                        ref="#gloss3">unaaja</term> so that when it gave birth they would share the
                    calves. He further added that <term ref="#gloss4">ubɔr</term> realised his fault
                    and gave him an unaasal in addition. </p>
                <p>
                    <q>
                        <term ref="#gloss1">Maatiin gur ki m muun chaa,</term>
                    </q>
                    Yaawork concludes her story rather abruptly after admitting that she has
                    forgotten the musical interlude of the tale. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="Note">
                <head type="subTitle">Note</head>
                <list type="index">
                    <label>1.</label>
                    <item>
                        <gloss target="#footnote1">In the Konkomba storytelling culture, one can
                            plunge directly
                            into his or her story without seeking permission in the form of
                            announcing an intent to tell the story and
                            receiving permission in the form of a response from the audience. This
                            is mostly the case when a storytelling session
                            has been ongoing for a while, or if a storyteller has already told one
                            or more stories and is seeking to add another one.</gloss>
                    </item>
                </list>
            </div>
            <div type="glossary">
                <head type="subTitle">A Glossary of Likpakpaln Words</head>
                <list type="gloss">
                    <label>maatiin gur ki m muun chaa:</label>
                    <item>
                        <gloss xml:id="gloss1">translated as, <q>May my story diminish while I grow
                            very tall.</q> This is a shortened version of the standard conclusion <hi
                                rend="italic">Maatiin gur ki m muun ke n-yaaja aagbem na</hi>
                            (translated as, <q>May my story diminish while I grow as tall as my
                            grandfather’s Kapok tree</q>). This standard conclusion is one of the
                            numerous ways in which a Konkomba storyteller can end his/her story. The
                            ending and its numerous variants suggest that Konkombas believe that
                            storytelling (or entertainment in general) has health benefits,
                            especially healthy physical growth. The association of storytelling with
                            physical growth is so entrenched in the Konkomba belief system that it
                            is even believed that when a child engages in storytelling in the
                            daytime – for Konkomba storytelling sessions are held normally in the
                            evenings after supper – he or she will suffer stunted growth. </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <label>Nlanjirbɔr:</label>
                    <item>
                        <gloss xml:id="gloss2">a male name which is a truncation of the Likpakpaln
                            phrase, <q>Kpa nlan jir ubɔr</q> (transliterated as <q>Wiser than the
                            chief</q>).</gloss>
                    </item>
                    <label>unaaja:</label>
                    <item>
                        <gloss xml:id="gloss3">Likpakpaln word for a bull. Its stem is <hi
                                rend="bold">unaa.</hi> Unaa is a gender-fluid noun so to assign
                            gender distinctions, one will have to add Likpakpaln gender markers such
                            as <q>ja</q> (for masculine) or <q>sal</q> (for feminine) to the noun.
                            Thus, a cow is called unaasal while a bull is called unaaja. In the
                            context of this story, the storyteller uses unaaja and unaasal to
                            distinguish between the bull and the cow in the tale. But occasionally
                            she uses the non-gender-specific noun, unaa. In such situations, the
                            context determines whether she is referring to the bull or the cow. The
                            plural form of unaa is <hi rend="bold">inaa</hi> while the plural forms
                            of unaaja and unaasal are <hi rend="bold">inaaja</hi> and <hi
                                rend="bold">inaasal</hi> respectively. </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <label>ubɔr:</label>
                    <item>
                        <gloss xml:id="gloss4">the political head of a Konkomba community.
                            Ubɔr is usually the eldest male member of the royal family. He inherits
                            that position from
                            his father after the latter’s demise. Thus, Konkombas practice the
                            patrilineal system of inheritance.</gloss>
                    </item>
                </list>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>