<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Rabbit Cheats Chameleon at a Marriage Contest</title>
                <author>Konkomba Oral Tradition (Ghana)</author>
                <storyteller>Abena</storyteller>
                <editor> Tasun Tidorchibe </editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <name> Tasun Tidorchibe </name>
                    <resp>transcript, editing and translation</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <name>Jessica Hüttig</name>
                    <name>Lucas Worm</name>
                    <resp> coding and editing </resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt> 
                    <name> Prof. Dr. Eva Ulrike Pirker </name>
                    <resp> supervision </resp>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor type="digitisation"> E-Learning Förderfonds HHU </sponsor>
               <sponsor type="funding">Katholischer Akademischer Ausländerdienst</sponsor>
                <address><name type="institution"> Centre for Translation Studies Düsseldorf </name> 
                    <name type="institution"> Heinrich-Heine-Universität Düsseldorf </name>
                    <street> Universitätsstraße 1 </street>
                    <postCode> 40225 </postCode>
                    <name type="city"> Düsseldorf </name>
                    <name type="country"> Germany </name></address>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher> Centre for Translation Studies Düsseldorf </publisher>
                <status>not yet published</status> 
                <pubPlace> Düsseldorf </pubPlace>
                <address> <name type="institution"> Centre for Translation Studies Düsseldorf </name> 
                <name type="institution"> Heinrich-Heine-Universität Düsseldorf </name>
                <street> Universitätsstraße 1 </street>
                <postCode> 40225 </postCode>
                <name type="city"> Düsseldorf </name>
                <name type="country"> Germany </name>
                </address>
                <availability> not yet available </availability>
                <date> TBD </date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
              <bibl> <title>Rabbit Cheats Chameleon at a Marriage Contest</title> <storyteller>Abena</storyteller> Translated by <editor role="translator"> Tasun Tidorchibe </editor> </bibl> 
            </sourceDesc>
            <encodingDesc>
                <styleDefDecl scheme="css" Version="2.1"> </styleDefDecl>
                <tagsDesc>  
                </tagsDesc>
            <editorialDecl> No author can be assigned to the story due to it being an oral tradition; The decision was taken to treat notes the same as a glossary in terms of coding</editorialDecl>
            <projectDesc>The project focuses on digitising oral folktales from Ghana, specifically the Konkomba people, through different media.
                The project puts a body of oral folktales into writing and eventually makes them available as annotated, digitised narratives.
                It thus aims to make a contribution to visibilising this culture, which through processes of colonisation, the accompanying priviledging of written/print culture and Eurocentric/Western thinking has been marginalised.</projectDesc>
            </encodingDesc>
            <profileDesc> 
                <creation> Originally told in
                <place xml:id="Chakping">
                     <placeName>Chakping</placeName>
                     <location>
                         <geo>9.67, -0.27</geo>    
                     </location>
                </place>  
                  transcribed folktale from Likpakpaln as told by <name type="storyteller">Abena </name> on <date when="2022">16th March 2022</date> in <name type="city">Chakping</name>, <name type="country">Ghana</name>
               </creation>
               <langUsage>
                   <language ident="lik">Likpakpaln</language>
                   <language ident="en">English</language>
               </langUsage>
               <textClass>placeholder tbd</textClass>
            </profileDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <head type="mainTitle">Rabbit Cheats Chameleon at a Marriage Contest</head>
            <p>(As narrated by Abena at Chakping on 16/03/2022)</p>
            <div type="introduction">
                <head type="subTitle">Introduction</head>
                <p>The story below details how the rabbit beats the chameleon at a marriage contest centred around uncovering the names of their political leader’s daughters. 
                    The story has it that the chameleon employs tact to uncover the names of the girls. 
                    However, his careless handling of the information results in his inability to receive the ultimate reward of marrying the girls – 
                    a loss that causes him so much agony that his head eventually deforms. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="story">
                <head type="subTitle">Story</head>
                <p><q>There once lived an ubɔr who had two daughters,</q> Abena commences and proceeds thus: 
                    One day he summoned all animals and told them that anyone who was able to tell him the names of the girls would get to marry them. 
                    Various animals subsequently took up the challenge and tried to no avail to guess the girls’ names.</p>
                <p>One day the girls decided to go to the riverside and do their laundry. On learning this, <term ref="#gloss3">umuatoon</term> quickly went ahead of them and hid in a nearby shrub. 
                    At the river, one of the girls finished washing her underwear and dried it on the shrub in which <term ref="#gloss3">umuatoon</term> was hiding. 
                    <term ref="#gloss3">Umuatoon</term> immediately took the underwear and hid it. If the girl couldn’t find the underwear, wouldn’t she be forced to call her sister’s name and ask? 
                    <hi rend="italic">(Abena asks her audience, in an attempt to explain <term ref="#gloss3">umuatoon’s</term> reason for hiding the underwear.)</hi></p>
                <p><q>Mmm!</q> responds one of Abena’s audience, after which she continues thus:</p>
                <p>When the girl returned and didn’t see the underwear, she called out to her sister, <q>Tibɔrkuun, have you seen my underwear?</q> 
                    Her sister responded in the negative: <q>I haven’t seen it.</q> 
                    After a while, the other sister called out to her sister and asked, <q>Doyala, have you seen it yet? I didn’t pick it.</q> 
                    In the end, didn’t <term ref="#gloss3">umuatoon</term> get to know their names as a result? <hi rend="italic">(Abana asks her audience again.)</hi></p>
                <p><q>He did,</q> a child from the audience responds.</p>
                <p><q><term ref="#gloss3">Umuatoon</term> got to know the girls’ names,</q> Abena affirms and continues as follows:</p>
                <p>The girls were soon done and returned home. <term ref="#gloss3">Umuatoon</term> climbed out of the shrub and also headed homewards. 
                    On his way, having forgotten how slowly he walks, <term ref="#gloss3">umuatoon</term> started singing:</p>
                <div type="song">
                    <table type="translation">
                        <row role="head">
                            <cell><hi rend="bold">Likpakpaln transcription</hi></cell>
                            <cell><hi rend="bold">English translation</hi></cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell><l>Udaan u bɔr Tibɔrkuun ee</l></cell>
                            <cell><l>The person who hid Tibɔrkuun</l></cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell><l>Ukpaakun bɔnn Doyala.</l></cell>
                            <cell><l>Ukpaakun has befriended Doyala.</l></cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell><l>M-mmm, Ukpaakun bɔnn Doyala</l></cell>
                            <cell><l>M-mmm, Ukpaakun has befriended Doyala.</l></cell>
                        </row>
                        <row></row>
                        <row>
                            <cell><l>Unii u bɔr Tibɔrkuun ee</l></cell>
                            <cell><l>The person who hid Tibɔrkuun</l></cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell><l>Ukpaakun bɔnn Doyala.</l></cell>
                            <cell><l>Ukpaakun has befriended Doyala.</l></cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell><l>M-mmm, Ukpaakun bɔnn Doyalaa!!!</l></cell>
                            <cell><l>M-mmm, Ukpaakun has befriended Doyalaa!!!</l></cell>
                        </row>
                        <row></row>
                    </table>
                </div>
                <p>As he was singing the song, <term ref="#gloss2">sandee</term> – who was resting in a shrub along the path – heard the song and quickly ran ahead of <term ref="gloss3">umuatoon</term> to ubɔr’s palace. 
                    On arrival he said, <q>Ubɔr, I‘ve discovered your daughters’ names.</q> 
                    Ubɔr then asked him what the names were, whereupon <term ref="#gloss2">sandee</term> replied that one was called Tibɔrkuun while the other was called Doyala.</p>
                <p>Meanwhile, <term ref="gloss3">umuatoon</term> was still on his way to the palace. He was still singing his song:</p>
                <div type="song">
                    <table type="translation">
                        <row role="head">
                            <cell><hi rend="bold">Likpakpaln transcription</hi></cell>
                            <cell><hi rend="bold">English translation</hi></cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell><l>Udaan u bɔr Tibɔrkuun ee</l></cell>
                            <cell><l>The person who hid Tibɔrkuun</l></cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell><l>Ukpaakun bɔnn Doyala.</l></cell>
                            <cell><l>Ukpaakun has befriended Doyala.</l></cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell><l>M-mmm, Ukpaakun bɔnn Doyala</l></cell>
                            <cell><l>M-mmm, Ukpaakun has befriended Doyala.</l></cell>
                        </row>
                        <row></row>
                        <row>
                            <cell><l>Unii u bɔr Tibɔrkuun ee</l></cell>
                            <cell><l>The person who hid Tibɔrkuun</l></cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell><l>Ukpaakun bɔnn Doyala.</l></cell>
                            <cell><l>Ukpaakun has befriended Doyala.</l></cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell><l>M-mmm, Ukpaakun bɔnn Doyalaa!!!</l></cell>
                            <cell><l>M-mmm, Ukpaakun has befriended Doyalaa!!!</l></cell>
                        </row>
                        <row></row>
                    </table>
                </div>
                <p>Eventually he arrived at the palace, where he was informed by ubɔr that <term ref="#gloss2">sandee</term>  had already 
                   revealed the girls’ names. But <term ref="#gloss3">umuatoon</term> insisted that he was the one who uncovered the girls’  
                   names. Ubɔr then asked, <q><term ref="#gloss2">Sandee</term> has been here for a while now; where have you been all this time?</q></p>
                <p><term ref="#gloss2">Sandee</term> was therefore adjudged the winner of the contest. A sorrow-stricken <term ref="#gloss3">umuatoon</term> burst
                    into uncontrollable tears. He wept so much that his head eventually deformed into a helmet
                    shape. <term ref="#gloss3">Umuatoon</term>'s head was originally not shaped like a bicycle helmet.</p>
                <p><term ref="#gloss2">Sandee</term> has always been wiser than <term ref="#gloss3">umuatoon</term>. <term ref="#gloss3">Umuatoon</term> can’t walk fast but he was smart to
                    hide the girl’s underwear in order to discover the girls’ names. Unfortunately, in the end, <term ref="#gloss2">sandee</term> 
                    outsmarted him and got the girls.</p>
                <p><q><term ref="#gloss1">Maatiin gur ka m muun chaa</term>,</q> Abena signs off. But one of her audience cuts in even before 
                    she ends the signing off statement:</p>
                <p><q>He should have kept quiet while slowly making his way to the palace. He shouldn’t have
                    composed a song with the girls’ names,</q> he says the latter sentence simultaneously with some
                    other audience.</p>
                <p><q>Enn! He mistakenly sang the song – which made it possible for the wise <term ref="#gloss2">sandee</term> to cheat him,</q> 
                    the storyteller concurs with her audience.</p>
                <p><q>Mm! Well, let’s end the post-narrative discussion and listen to other stories,</q> another person 
                    from the audience interjects. The discussion consequently ends and the next storyteller
                    commences.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="glossary">
                <head type="subTitle">A Glossary of Likpakpaln Words and Phrases (or Expressions)</head>
                <list type="gloss">
                <label>maatiin gur ka m muun chaa:</label><item><gloss xml:id="gloss1">translated as,<q>May my story diminish while I grow very tall.</q>
                    This is a shortened version of the standard conclusion <q><hi rend="italic">Maatiin gur ki m muun ke n-yaaja aagbem na</hi></q> (translated as, <q>May my story diminish while I grow as tall as my grandfather’s Kapok tree</q>).
                    This standard conclusion is one of the numerous ways in which a Konkomba storyteller can end his/her story. The ending and its numerous variants, such as the one in the 
                    story above, suggest that Konkombas believe that storytelling (or entertainment in general) has health benefits, especially healthy physical growth. The association of storytelling with
                    physical growth is so entrenched in the Konkomba belief system that it is even believed that when a child engages in storytelling during the day – for Konkomba storytelling sessions are
                    held normally in the evenings after supper – he or she will suffer stunted growth.</gloss></item>
                <label>sandee:</label><item><gloss xml:id="gloss2">Likpakpaln word for a rabbit, bunny or hare. Sandee is the wisest and trickster character in Konkomba folklore.
                    It is notorious for often using its cunning and witty nature to wriggle its way out of difficult situations or to cheat others – as it does in this story.</gloss></item>
                <label>umuatoon:</label><item><gloss xml:id="gloss3">Likpakpaln word for a chameleon.</gloss></item>
                </list>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>






                






            