<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
       <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Rabbit outwits the Hyena</title>
                <author>Konkomba Oral Tradition (Ghana)</author>
                <storyteller>Jalula Jagri</storyteller>
                <editor>Tasun Tidorchibe</editor>
                 <respStmt>
                    <name> Tasun Tidorchibe </name>
                    <resp>transcript, editing and translation</resp>
                </respStmt>
                    <respStmt>
                    <name>Aziza Fakiri</name> 
                    <name>Yara Köster</name>
                    <resp> coding and editing </resp>
                <respStmt>
                <name> Dr. Eva Ulrike Pirker </name>
                    <resp> supervision </resp>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor type="digitisation"> E-Learning Förderfonds HHU </sponsor>
               <sponsor type="funding">Katholischer Akademischer Ausländerdienst</sponsor>
                <address><name type="institution"> Centre for Translation Studies Düsseldorf </name> 
                    <name type="institution"> Heinrich-Heine-Universität Düsseldorf </name>
                    <street> Universitätsstraße 1 </street>
                    <postCode> 40225 
                    </postCode>
                <name type="city"> Düsseldorf </name>
                    <name type="country"> Germany</name>
                    </address>
                    </respStmt>                
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher> Centre for Translation Studies Düsseldorf </publisher>
                <status>not yet published</status> 
                <pubPlace> Düsseldorf </pubPlace>
<address> <name type="institution"> Centre for Translation Studies Düsseldorf </name> 
    <name type="institution"> Heinrich-Heine-Universität Düsseldorf </name>
    <street> Universitätsstraße 1 </street>
    <postCode> 40225 </postCode>
    <name type="city"> Düsseldorf </name>
    <name type="country"> Germany </name>
</address>
<availability> not yet available </availability>
<date> TBD </date>
            <sourceDesc>
              <bibl> <title>The Rabbit outwits the Hyena</title> <storyteller>Jalula Jagri</storyteller> Translated by <editor role="translator"> Tasun Tidorchibe </editor> </bibl> 
            </sourceDesc>
            </publicationStmt>
        </fileDesc>
            <encodingDesc>
                <styleDefDecl scheme="css" Version="2.1"> </styleDefDecl>
                <tagsDesc>      
                </tagsDesc>
            <editorialDecl> No author can be assigned to the story due to it being an oral tradition; The decision was taken to treat notes the same as a glossary in terms of coding</editorialDecl>
            <projectDesc>The project focuses on digitising oral folktales from Ghana, specifically the Konkomba people, through different media.
                The project puts a body of oral folktales into writing and eventually makes them available as annotated, digitised narratives.
                It thus aims to make a contribution to visibilising this culture, which through processes of colonisation, the accompanying priviledging of written/print culture and Eurocentric/Western thinking has been marginalised.</projectDesc>
                </encodingDesc>
                <profileDesc> 
                <creation> Originally told in
                <place xml:id="Kakpeekni, Saboba">
                     <placeName> Kakpeekni, Saboba</placeName>
                     <location>
                         <geo>9.72,0.31</geo>    
                     </location>
                 </place>  
                  transcribed folktale from Likpakpaln as told by <name type="storyteller">Jalula Jagri</name> on <date when="2022">19th March 2022</date> in <name type="city">Kakpeekni, Saboba</name>, <name type="country">Ghana</name>      
               </creation>
               <langUsage>
                   <language ident="lik">Likpakpaln</language>
                   <language ident="en">English</language>
               </langUsage>
               <textClass>placeholder tbd</textClass>
            </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
     <body>
       <head type="mainTitle">The Rabbit outwits the Hyena</head>
       <p>(As told by Jalula Jagri at Kakpeekni, Saboba on 19/03/2022)</p>
       <div type="introduction">
       <head type="subTitle"> Introduction </head>
       <p>The story below details how the rabbit outsmarts the hyena in a battle between strength and
        intelligence. The two friends are given meat as a reward for a kind gesture but the hyena beats
        the rabbit and confiscates his share of the meat. Through a clever trick, the rabbit however
        reclaims all the meat in the end. To watch the Likpakpaln narration <ref target="https://mediathek.hhu.de/watch/1db90bb0-6fe7-409c-aab9-7b6254d08d58">click here.</ref></p>
        </div>
        <div type="story">
          <head type="subTitle">Story</head>
          <p><q>My story is as follows:</q>Jalula announces and proceeds thus:</p>
          <p>There once lived <term ref="#gloss4">sandee</term> and <cell><l><term ref="#gloss1">baanan (aka tɔkɔ)</term></l></cell>. The two were very good friends who did things
                in common. They lived in a foreign land. One day, the two friends were returning from a
                drinking spree when sandee suddenly tripped over something (and fell). He then told his friend,
                <q>Baanaan, my pal, pause for a second. I stepped on something slippery here.</q>On groping the
                ground, he found litabaaboln. The two friends took the object and proceeded to the village.</p> 
          <p>On reaching the village, they discovered that the litabaaboln belonged to the<cell><l><term ref="#gloss5">ubɔr</term></l></cell> of the village –
            for the latter had sent went throughout the village that he had lost his <cell><l><term ref="#gloss2">litabaaboln.</term></l></cell>. He even
            promised that any person or group of persons who found and returned it to him would be given a
            special reward.</p>   
          <p>Sandee and baanaan came to a consensus and returned the object to ubɔr. This pleased ubɔr very
            much. On taking custody of his litabaaboln, he asked the two friends where they hailed from.
            The two replied that they came from Kitiŋpilnbu. Ubɔr then revealed that he had a gift for them
            and that the gift belonged solely to the two of them. They were supposed to return to their home
            village and enjoy the gift there. Ubɔr then ordered that two bulls and three rams be killed. The
            meat was to be shared equally between sandee and baanaan. When that was done, ubɔr thanked
            them again and they set off.</p>
          <p>The two had barely left the premises of the palace when baanaan broke into song:</p>
          <p><hi ref="italic">(The storyteller intones the song and his audience join in.)</hi></p>
        <div type="song">
 <table type="translation">
 <row role="head">
 <cell><hi rend="bold">Likpakpaln transcription</hi></cell>
 <cell><hi rend="bold">English translation</hi></cell>
 </row>
 <row><cell></cell></row>
 <row>
 <cell><l>Unaabɔr nti ti ninmeen chɔi –</l></cell>
 <cell><l>Unaabɔr has given us something fatty</l></cell>
 </row>
 <row>
 <cell><l>Ti tin ji Kitiŋpilnbu.</l></cell>
 <cell><l>To eat at Kitiŋpilnbu.(3x)</l></cell>
 </row>
 <row>
<cell><l>Unaabɔr nti ti ninmeen chɔi</l></cell>
<cell><l> Unaabɔr has given us something fatty</l></cell>
</row>
 <row>
 <cell><l>Ti tin ji Kitiŋpilnbuuu!!!</l></cell>
 <cell><l>To eat at Kitiŋpilnbuuu!!!</l></cell>
 </row>  
</table>
</div>
<p>When they had journeyed homeward to a point where they could no longer see the houses behind
them, baanaan asked sandee whether or not ubɔr had specifically mentioned his name. Sandee
responded in the affirmative. The former then said, <q>Let’s go then.</q> As they resumed walking,
baanaan started singing again:</p>
<p><hi ref="italic">(The storyteller intones the song again and his audience join in.)</hi></p>
<div type="song">
 <table type="translation">
 <row role="head">
 <cell><hi rend="bold">Likpakpaln transcription</hi></cell>
 <cell><hi rend="bold">English translation</hi></cell>
 <row><cell></cell></row></row>
 <row>
 <cell><l>Unaabɔr nti ti ninmeen chɔi –</l></cell>
 <cell><l>Unaabɔr has given us something fatty</l></cell>
 </row>
 <row>
 <cell><l>Ti tin ji Kitiŋpilnbu.</l></cell>
 <cell><l>To eat at Kitiŋpilnbu.(2x)</l></cell>
 </row>
 <row>
<cell><l>Unaabɔr nti ti ninmeen chɔi</l></cell>
<cell><l> Unaabɔr has given us something fatty</l></cell>
</row>
 <row>
 <cell><l>Ti tin ji Kitiŋpilnbuuu!!!</l></cell>
 <cell><l>To eat at Kitiŋpilnbuuu!!!</l></cell>
 </row> 
<row><cell></cell></row> 
</table>
</div>
<p>After the two friends had journeyed further, baanaan told sandee that all the meat belonged to
him and that sandee had no claim to it. He argued that sandee was too small in stature and that he
(baanaan) was the one who picked up the litabaaboln. He added that the only reason he allowed
sandee to speak at ubɔr’s palace was because he (baanaan) wasn’t articulate in speech.</p>
<p>Heated exchanges ensued between the two as a result, ultimately degenerating into fisticuffs.
Baanaan bit off one of sandee’s ears and the latter fled the scene as fast as his legs could carry
him. His initial plan was to run back and tell ubɔr what his friend had done to him. But on
second thought, he stopped, took another route and ran ahead of baanaan. He then picked a red
rope and tied on it a white kola nut, the skull of a dog and the tail of a horse. After that he tied
the rope across the path baanaan was journeying on. Having done that, he hid in the bush and
waited for him.</p>
<p>Baanaan, who was dancing all along while carrying the meat, soon got to the spot where sandee
was hiding. He hit the rope sandee had tied across the path and staggered under the weight of the
meat. On regaining his balance, he looked at the rope and its accessories in bewilderment and
asked, <q>Grandpa, what are you doing here? Are you looking for me?</q> But the rope didn’t
respond. He then asked, <q>Do you want meat?</q> Again, the rope didn’t respond. He enquired
further,<q>Do you want the head of the bull?</q></p>
<p>At this point sandee pulled the rope and it shook, whereupon baanaan dropped the head of the
bull. He then told the rope,<q>Well, please let me through.</q>But the rope didn’t respond. Baanaan
then asked again, <q>Do you want meat?</q>The rope shook in response. <q>What do you want; the
bull’s leg?</q> Sandee pulled the rope and it shook again. Baanaan obliged and dropped the bull’s
leg. This continued until baanaan had no meat left on him.</p>
<p>Unfortunately, the rope would still not let him through. He became terrified and enquired again,
<q>Grandpa, who do you want? Me?</q> Sandee pulled the rope again, whereupon baanaan wet
himself and took off running as fast as he could.</p>
<p><q>This is the end of my story,</q>Jalula concludes and adds:</p>
<p><q>The story seeks to teach us that we should have mutual respect for all. No one should use his or
her intelligence or physical strength to cheat others. Baanaan wanted to use his might to cheat
sandee but the latter outwitted him. <cell><l><term ref="#gloss3">Maatiin kpelb aanaa wɔŋ</term></l></cell>.</q></p>
</div>
<div type="glossary">
<head type="subTitle">A Glossary of Likpakpaln Words and Phrases (or Expressions)</head>
<list type="gloss">
<label>baanaan (aka tɔkɔ):</label><item><gloss xml:id="gloss1">Likpakpaln word for a hyena. In Konkomba folklore, baanaan
is the most unintelligent animal character. It almost always falls prey to the antics of others,
especially sandee (i.e., rabbit).</gloss></item>
<label>litabaaboln.:</label><item><gloss xml:id="gloss2">a wooden pipe for smoking tobacco, marijuana, etc.</gloss></item>
<label>maatiin kpelb aanaa wɔŋ:</label><item><gloss xml:id="gloss3">translated as <q>The end of my story seeks/requires a continuation.</q>
This is one of the numerous ways in which a Konkomba storyteller can end a tale.</gloss></item>
<label>sandee:</label><item><gloss xml:id="gloss4">Likpakpaln word for a rabbit, bunny, or hare. Sandee is the wisest and trickster character
in Konkomba folklore. It is notorious for often using its cunning and witty nature to deceive
other characters or wriggle its way out of difficult situations.</gloss></item>
<label>ubɔr:</label><item><gloss xml:id="gloss5">the political head of a Konkomba community. Ubɔr is usually the eldest male member of
the royal family. He inherits that position from his father after the latter’s demise. Thus,
Konkombas practise the patrilineal system of inheritance.</gloss></item>
</list>
</div>
</body>
</text>
</TEI>