<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>
                    THE RABBIT STEALS THE HORSE’S MOUTH
                </title>
                <author>Konkomba Oral Tradition (Ghana)</author>
                <storyteller>Bilinyi Chiikpaab</storyteller>
                <editor>Tasun Tidorchibe</editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <name>Tasun Tidorchibe</name>
                    <resp>transcript, editing and translation</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <name>Anna Schmitt</name>
                    <name>Lara Wenisch</name>
                    <name>Hannah Lea Küppers </name>
                    <resp>coding and editing</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <name>Prof. Dr. Eva Ulrike Pirker</name>
                    <resp>supervision</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor type="digitisation">E-Learning Förderfonds HHU</sponsor>
                <sponsor type="funding">Katholischer Akademischer Ausländerdienst</sponsor>
                <address>
                    <name type="institution">Centre for Translation Studies Düsseldorf</name>
                    <name type="institution">Heinrich-Heine-Universität Düsseldorf</name>
                    <street>Universitätsstraße 1</street>
                    <postCode>40225</postCode>
                    <name type="city">Düsseldorf</name>
                    <name type="country">Germany</name>
                </address>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Centre for Translation Studies Düsseldorf</publisher>
                <status>not yet published</status>
                <pubPlace>Düsseldorf</pubPlace>
                <address>
                    <name type="institution">Centre for Translation Studies Düsseldorf</name>
                    <name type="institution">Heinrich-Heine-Universität Düsseldorf</name>
                    <street>Universitätsstraße 1</street>
                    <postCode>40225</postCode>
                    <name type="city">Düsseldorf</name>
                    <name type="country">Germany</name>
                </address>
                <availability>not yet available</availability>
                <date>TBD</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>
                    <title>THE RABBIT STEALS THE HORSE’S MOUTH</title>
                    <storyteller>Bilinyi Chiikpaab</storyteller>Translated
                    by <editor role="translator">Tasun
                        Tidorchibe
                    </editor>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <styleDefDecl scheme="css" Version="2.1"></styleDefDecl>
            <tagsDesc></tagsDesc>
            <editorialDecl>No author can be assigned to the story due to it being an oral tradition;
                The decision was
                taken to treat notes the same as a glossary in terms of coding
            </editorialDecl>
            <projectDesc>The project focuses on digitising oral folktales from Ghana, specifically
                the Konkomba people,
                through different media. The project puts a body of oral folktales into writing and
                eventually makes
                them available as annotated, digitised narratives. It thus aims to make a
                contribution to visibilising
                this culture, which through processes of colonisation, the accompanying priviledging
                of written/print
                culture and Eurocentric/Western thinking has been marginalised.
            </projectDesc>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation>Originally told at <place xml:id="Kutol">
                    <placeName>Kutol</placeName>
                    <location>
                        <geo>9,58, 0,24</geo>
                    </location>
                </place>
                transcribed folktale from Likpakpaln as told by <name type="storyteller">Bilinyi
                Chiikpaab</name> on <date when="2022">17th March 2022
                </date> in <name type="city">City name not
                available</name> , <name type="country">Ghana</name>
            </creation>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="lik">Likpakpaln</language>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>placeholder tbd</textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <head type="mainTitle">
                The Rabbit Steals the Horse's Mouth
            </head>
            <p>(as told by Bilinyi Chiikpaab at Kutol on 17/03/2022)</p>
            <div type="introduction">
                <head type="subTitle">
                    Introduction
                </head>
                <p>The following story presents us with one of the rare occasions when the rabbit,
                    who is the wisest
                    animal character in Konkomba folklore, is at the receiving end of his antics. In
                    this story, the
                    rabbit’s greed lands him in trouble when he decides to eat a billy goat alone in
                    the bush.
                    Unfortunately for him, a testicle wielding the power of life and death prevents
                    him from enjoying
                    the chevon. Added to this, the rabbit ends up with a big, swollen mouth. But
                    typical of the rabbit,
                    he employs wit to steal the horse’s cute mouth during a communal event. The
                    story essentially warns
                    against selfishness.
                </p>
            </div>
            <div type="story">

                <head type="subTitle">
                    Story
                </head>
                <p>
                    <q>My story is as follows:</q> Bilinyi announces to his audience and proceeds
                    thus: </p>
                <p>There’s a reason <term ref="#gloss9">utaan</term> often sighs, hm hm hm! There’s
                    an unresolved problem. <term ref="#gloss6">Sandee</term> is the cause of <term
                        ref="#gloss9">utaan</term>’s heavy sighs. The story has it that <term
                        ref="#gloss6">sandee</term> once bought a billy goat to slaughter and eat.
                    But because he didn’t want to share the meat with his family, he decided to go
                    and eat it in the bush alone. He lied to his family that he had to make a
                    sacrifice in the bush to appease the gods. </p>
                <p>He took the billy goat to the bush and slaughtered it. <term ref="#gloss8">Uja</term>,
                    if you saw how fatty the billy goat was! <hi rend="italic">(Bilinyi addresses
                    the last sentence to his audience directly amid body movements
                        of exaggeration. This elicits laughter from the audience, after which he
                    continues as follows:)
                    </hi>After
                    chopping the meat into pieces, he started cooking it. </p>
                <p>A cricket accidentally jumped out of one of the holes under the stones he used as
                    his stove for cooking. Well, you know how fatty the cricket is <hi rend="italic">(Bilinyi
                    addresses his audience
                        again.)</hi>The cricket’s fat was all over the place. <term ref="#gloss6">
                    Sandee</term>, unable to restrain himself, ate the cricket as an appetiser. He
                    then decided to hunt for more crickets and eat in order to whet his appetite for
                    the chevon that was still cooking. He started searching under every nearby
                    stone. Unfortunately, under one of the stones, he saw a big testicle instead of
                    a cricket. If you saw that testicle! He was a very big testicle – big and
                    mature. If you saw the mass and height! He was visibly above ground level. <hi
                        rend="italic">(The storyteller addresses the above directly to his
                        audience again, employing gestures aimed at describing the size of the
                    testicle while the
                        audience laugh.)
                    </hi>
                </p>
                <p>On seeing the testicle, <term ref="#gloss6">sandee</term> attempted to cover him
                    again with the stone. But the testicle told him to do no such thing. <term
                        ref="#gloss6">Sandee</term> ignored him and tried to return the stone to its
                    previous position on top of the testicle. Before he could do that, the testicle
                    said: <q>Then die <term ref="#gloss1">bra bla kum</term>.</q>
                    <term ref="#gloss6">
                    Sandee</term> immediately fell over dead. The testicle then said again, <q><term
                            ref="#gloss2">Fikrku</term>.</q> At this command – or rather incantation
                    – <term ref="#gloss6">sandee</term> came back to life again. The testicle then
                    ordered <term ref="#gloss6">sandee</term> to pick him up. <term ref="#gloss6">
                    Sandee</term> complied and carried the testicle on his back. </p>
                <p>The testicle then saw smoke at a distance and ordered <term ref="#gloss6">sandee</term>
                    to take him there. But <term ref="#gloss6">sandee</term> said the smoke was
                    emanating from a fire ubɔr’s herdsmen had made and that they would be angry if
                    they (<term ref="#gloss6">sandee</term> and the testicle) went there. He didn’t
                    want to share the chevon with the testicle. <hi
                        rend="italic">(Bilinyi says the latter amid laughter, together with some of
                    his audience.)
                    </hi>
                    The testicle sensed <term ref="#gloss6">sandee</term>’s reluctance and said: <q>Well,
                    if that’s the case, bla kum.</q>
                    <term ref="#gloss6">Sandee</term> died
                    instantly. The testicle again said, <q>
                        <term ref="#gloss2">Fikrku</term>
                    </q> – and sandee came
                    back to life. The testicle ordered him again to take him to the place from which
                    the smoke was emanating. Left with no other option, <term ref="#gloss6">sandee</term>
                    took him to the place he was cooking his meat. </p>
                <p>When they arrived at the spot, the chevon had been well-cooked and ready for
                    consumption. The testicle then asked, <q><term ref="#gloss6">Sandee</term>, what
                    is being cooked?</q> <term ref="#gloss6">Sandee</term> replied that it was meat
                    and that it belonged to ubɔr’s herdsmen. The testicle ordered him to take the
                    meat off the stove but <term ref="#gloss6">sandee</term> protested, saying that
                    ubɔr’s herdsmen would be displeased. Infuriated, the testicle said, <q>Bra
                        kum,
                    </q> whereupon <term
                        ref="#gloss6">sandee</term> fell over dead. He then said, <q>
                        <term ref="#gloss2">Fikrku</term>
                    </q> – and <term
                        ref="#gloss6">sandee</term> regained consciousness. The testicle then told <term
                        ref="#gloss6">sandee</term>, once again, to take the meat off the stove – to
                    which <term ref="#gloss6">sandee</term> complied. </p>
                <p>After that, the testicle told <term ref="#gloss6">sandee</term> to dish out the
                    meat so that he would eat. <term ref="#gloss6">Sandee</term> complied again and
                    said the testicle should eat the fleshy pieces so that he would eat only the
                    bones. The testicle ate his fill of all the fleshy and fatty meat and became big
                    beyond verbal description. After eating, the testicle topped it up with water
                    and ordered <term ref="#gloss6">sandee</term> to carry him on his back again.
                    But <term ref="#gloss6">sandee</term> declined, whereupon the testicle said, <q>Bla
                    kum.</q> <term ref="#gloss6">Sandee</term> died instantly. <q>Fikrku,</q> he
                    chanted again – and <term ref="#gloss6">sandee</term> was back to life. The
                    testicle asked <term ref="#gloss6">sandee</term>, once more, to carry him on his
                    back, to which <term ref="#gloss6">sandee</term> complied. </p>
                <p>As <term ref="#gloss6">sandee</term> was carrying him, he saw a hawk hovering
                    above them. By this time <term ref="#gloss6">sandee</term> was exhausted so he
                    broke into song: <hi rend="italic">(Before intoning the song, Bilinyi admonishes
                    his audience to
                        sing along with him. He then intones the song and the audience join in.)
                    </hi>
                </p>
                <div type="song">
                    <table type="translation">
                        <row role="head">
                            <cell>
                                <hi rend="bold">Likpakpaln transcription</hi>
                            </cell>
                            <cell>
                                <hi rend="bold">English translation</hi>
                            </cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>
                                <l>Kaasaa kaasaa, loon loonkaan</l>
                            </cell>
                            <cell>
                                <l>Hawk, hawk, swoop in stealthily</l>
                            </cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>
                                <l><term ref="#gloss5">Ntakpapeen</term> bu ee.</l>
                            </cell>
                            <cell>
                                <l>And drop on a rocky ground.</l>
                            </cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>
                                <l>Kaasaa kaasaa, loon loonkaan</l>
                            </cell>
                            <cell>
                                <l>Hawk, hawk, swoop in stealthily</l>
                            </cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>
                                <l><term ref="#gloss5">Ntakpapeen</term> bu ee.</l>
                            </cell>
                            <cell>
                                <l>And drop on a rocky ground.</l>
                            </cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>
                                <l>Kaasaa kaasaa, loon loonkaan</l>
                            </cell>
                            <cell>
                                <l>Hawk, hawk, swoop in stealthily</l>
                            </cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>
                                <l>Ntakpapeen bu eeee!!!!</l>
                            </cell>
                            <cell>
                                <l>And drop on a rocky ground!!!!</l>
                            </cell>
                        </row>
                        <row></row>
                    </table>
                </div>
                <p>That the hawk should quietly swoop in, snatch the testicle and drop him on a
                    rocky ground. That’s the meaning of the song. <hi rend="italic">(Bilinyi
                    explains to his audience amid gestures.)</hi>
                </p>
                <p>The hawk got the message. It swooped in, snatched the testicle and flew very high
                    while <term ref="#gloss6">sandee</term> urged it on: <q>Take him higher and
                    higher and higher and higher. Take him to a rocky ground; take him to
                        a rocky ground.</q>
                    <hi rend="italic">(Bilinyi mimics <term ref="#gloss6">
                    sandee</term>, amid gestures, as he renders these sentences.)</hi> When the hawk
                    got to the rocky area, it dropped the testicle and he fell and spurted, <term
                        ref="#gloss4">kpinn</term>! The billy goat’s fat was scattered all over the
                    place. <term ref="#gloss6">Sandee</term> rushed there and started licking the
                    fat while remarking, <q>Yes, that’s my billy goat’s fat.</q> By the time he was
                    done licking all the fat, his mouth became very big. </p>
                <p>On arriving home, <term ref="#gloss6">sandee</term>’s kids could not recognise
                    their father. <q>This can’t be our father’s
                        mouth,</q> they remarked. <term ref="#gloss6">Sandee</term> then hatched a
                    plan and told everyone in the community that night that ubɔr had asked that the
                    next day everyone should go to the dam and fetch water. He entreated all to turn
                    up so that they could fetch the water. Mark you, his plan was to steal <term
                        ref="#gloss9">utaan</term>’s mouth. <term ref="#gloss9">Utaan</term>’s mouth
                    wasn’t as big as it is today. <term ref="#gloss9">Utaan</term> is now saddled
                    with <term ref="#gloss6">sandee</term>’s big mouth. <hi rend="italic">
                        (Bilinyi tells his audience.)
                    </hi>
                </p>
                <p>When everyone converged at the dam, <term ref="#gloss6">sandee</term> told them
                    that the order was that everyone must leave their mouths at the shore before
                    fetching the water. Meanwhile, <term ref="#gloss6">sandee</term> had told his
                    children that at midmorning, they should set ablaze the pile of dry grass
                    outside his house. As <term ref="#gloss6">sandee</term> and the others were
                    fetching the water, the former kept looking intermittently in the direction of
                    his house. As soon as he saw the smoke from the fire at his house, he shouted
                    that ubɔr’s <term ref="#gloss3">kinakook</term> was on fire, adding that
                    everyone should grab the closest mouth and rush there. His target was <term
                        ref="#gloss9">utaan</term>’s mouth. So on saying that, he quickly picked <term
                        ref="#gloss9">utaan</term>’s mouth and took off running homeward. When <term
                        ref="#gloss9">utaan</term> went to pick a mouth, he realised that all that
                    was left was <term ref="#gloss6">sandee</term>’s big mouth. He therefore took it
                    and ran home as well. </p>
                <p>On arrival, he accused <term ref="#gloss6">sandee</term> of taking his mouth. But <term
                        ref="#gloss6">sandee</term> insisted that the mouth was his. He asked ubɔr
                    to take a good look at both mouths and determine which one was more likely his.
                    Before ubɔr could reply, he turned and asked <term ref="#gloss9">utaan</term>: <q>How
                    can a big fellow like you have this tiny mouth
                        while a tiny creature like me will have such a big mouth?</q> Ubɔr
                    subsequently ruled in favour of <term ref="#gloss6">sandee</term>, thereby
                    allowing the latter to keep <term ref="#gloss9">utaan</term>’s mouth while the
                    latter kept <term ref="#gloss6">sandee</term>’s. So <term ref="#gloss6">sandee</term>
                    is using <term ref="#gloss9">utaan</term>’s mouth. That is why occasionally
                    utaan will sigh heavily, <q>hm hm hm hm!</q> His problem is that he is now
                    saddled with a mouth that was originally not his. <hi rend="italic">(On hearing
                    this, Bilinyi’s audience burst into laughter while
                        the storyteller signs off thus:)
                    </hi>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <q>
                        <term ref="#gloss7">Tiin tiin kulb.</term>
                    </q>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div type="glossary">

                <head type="subTitle">A Glossary of Likpakpaln Words and Phrases</head>
                <list type="gloss">
                    <label>bra bla kum:</label>
                    <item>
                        <gloss xml:id="gloss1">this phrase has no semantic value in Likpakpaln since
                            it is merely an incantation employed by the testicle in this story.</gloss>
                    </item>
                    <label>
                        fikrku:
                    </label>
                    <item>
                        <gloss xml:id="gloss2">an incantation employed by the testicle to bring the
                            rabbit back to life. Its root is the Likpakpaln verb, fikr – which means <q>to
                            resurrect.</q> In this story, therefore, the word <q>fikrku</q> means <q>come
                            back to life</q> or <q>regain consciousness</q> or <q>
                                resurrect.</q></gloss>
                    </item>
                    <label>
                        kinakook (also spelt kinakuɔk):
                    </label>
                    <item>
                        <gloss xml:id="gloss3">a round room that serves as the main entrance to a
                            typical Konkomba house. It has two
                            doors at both ends to serve as the passage in or out of a house. It also
                            serves as a
                            place for relaxing or hosting visitors/guests. In ubɔr’s palace,
                            kinakook usually has a
                            stage/platform where ubɔr sits to hold meetings and perform other
                            functions.</gloss>
                    </item>
                    <label>
                        kpinn!
                    </label>
                    <item>
                        <gloss xml:id="gloss4">an onomatopoeic word employed by the storyteller to
                            capture the loud sound made by the
                            testicle when it fell on the rock and spurted.</gloss>
                    </item>
                    <label>
                        ntakpapeen:
                    </label>
                    <item>
                        <gloss xml:id="gloss5">Likpakpaln word for rocky ground. The word is also
                            variously spelled ntakpateer or
                            ntakpateen depending on the Likpakpaln dialect being used.</gloss>
                    </item>
                    <label>
                        sandee:
                    </label>
                    <item>
                        <gloss xml:id="gloss6">a rabbit, hare or bunny. Sandee is the wisest and
                            trickster character in Konkomba
                            folklore. It is notorious for often using its cunning and witty nature
                            to wriggle its
                            way out of difficult situations or to cheat others – as it does in this
                            story.</gloss>
                    </item>
                    <label>
                        tiin tiin kulb:
                    </label>
                    <item>
                        <gloss xml:id="gloss7">translated as <q>the end of my story.</q> This is one
                            of the commonest and easiest ways to end one’s story in the Konkomba
                            storytelling culture.</gloss>
                    </item>
                    <label>
                        uja:
                    </label>
                    <item>
                        <gloss xml:id="gloss8">Likpakpaln word for a man or a male. The plural form
                            is bijab (i.e., men, males, guys, etc.). However, in everyday usage, uja
                            is also commonly used as an emphasis marker or as an affectionate
                            address to a friend or colleague. In such situations, uja sheds off its
                            gender associations and assumes a new role as an intensifier of
                            something a speaker wants to emphasise or as a noun to refer to someone
                            as a buddy or a friend. In the context of this story, when the
                            storyteller addresses his audience as <q>uja,</q> he employs it in the
                            latter two senses – that is, to emphasise what he says and also as a
                            rhetorical tool to establish camaraderie with his audience.</gloss>
                    </item>
                    <label>
                        utaan:
                    </label>
                    <item>
                        <gloss xml:id="gloss9">Likpakpaln word for a horse.</gloss>
                    </item>
                </list>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>