<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"> 
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc> 
            <titleStmt>
                <title>NACHIIN PAYS FOR FEASTING ON UNYII'S CHILDREN</title>
                <storyteller>Konkomba people (Ghana)</storyteller>
                <author>Konkomba Oral Tradition</author>
                <editor>Tasun Tidorchibe</editor>
                <respStmt>  
                    <name>Tasun Tidorchibe</name>
                    <resp>transcript and translation</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <name> Nadine Hoffmann</name>
                    <resp>coding and editing</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <name>Dr. Eva Ulrike Pirker</name>
                    <resp>supervisor</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor type="digitisation">E-learning Förderfonds HHU</sponsor> 
                <sponsor type="funding">Katholischer Akademischer Ausländer-Dienst e.V.</sponsor>
                <address>
                    <name type="institution">Katholischer Akademischer Ausländer-Dienst e.V.</name>
                    <street>Hausdorffstr. 151</street>
                    <postCode>53129</postCode>
                    <name type="city">Bonn</name>
                    <name type="country">Germany</name>
                </address>
            </titleStmt> 
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Centre for Translation Studies Düsseldorf</publisher>
                <status>not yet published</status>
                <pubPlace>Düsseldorf</pubPlace>
                <address> <name type="institution"> Centre for Translation Studies Düsseldorf</name>
                    <name type="institution"> Heinrich Heine University Düsseldorf</name>
                    <street>Universitätsstraße 1</street> 
                    <postCode>40225</postCode> 
                    <name type="city">Düsseldorf</name>
                    <name type="country"> Germany</name>
                </address>
                <availability> not yet available </availability>
                <date> TBD </date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl> <title> Nachiin Pays for Feasting on Unyii's Children </title> <author> Konkomba People </author> 
                    Translated by <editor role="translator"> Tasun Tidorchibe </editor> </bibl> 
            </sourceDesc>
            <encodingDesc>
                <styleDefDecl scheme="css" Version="2​.1"/>
            </encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>No single author since it is based on a Konkomba oral tradition;
                 only footnotes for certain terms for better readability/understanding</editorialDecl>
            <projectDesc>The project focuses on digitising oral folktales from Ghana, specifically the Konkomba people, through different media. 
                The project puts a body of oral folktales into writing and eventually makes them available as annotated, digitised
                narratives. It thus aims to make a contribution to visibilising this culture, which through processes of colonisation, the accompanying
                priviledging of written/print culture and Eurocentric/Western thinking has been marginalised.</projectDesc>
            <profileDesc> 
                <creation> Originally told in
                    <place xml:id="Kotul">
                        <placeName>
                            Kotul
                        </placeName>
                    </place>
                    transcribed folktale from Likpakpaln as told by <name type="storyteller"> Bilinyi Chikpaab </name> on <date when="2022">18th March 2022 </date>in <name type="city">Kutol </name>, <name type="country">Ghana</name>
               </creation>
               <langUsage>
                   <language ident="lik">Likpakpaln</language>
                   <language ident="en">English</language>
               </langUsage>
            </profileDesc>
        </fileDesc>    
    </teiHeader>
    <text> 
        <body>
        <head type="mainTitle">Nachiin Pays for Feasting on Unyii's Children</head>
        <p> (As told by Bilinyi Chikpaab on 18th March 2022 in Kotul)</p>
        <head type="subTitle"> Introduction </head>
            <p>The following story relates how a wolf deceives a crocodile and eats all her children. Unfortunately for the wolf, a rabbit also employs wit
             to bring him to justice, resulting in him (the wolf) losing his testicles to the irate and distraught mother crocodile in the end. </p>

             <p>If you want to listen to the Likpakpaln narration,<ref target="https://mediathek.hhu.de/watch/cc23e874-6ae3-4bfd-a232-ce5768227abd"> click here.</ref></p>
             
        <head type="subTitle"> Story </head>
        <p>“Here goes my story,” Bilinyi announces.</p>
        <p>“Daya,” responds audience.</p>
        <p>“This story is about <term xml:id="glossary5">sande</term><note type="footnote" n="1" place="bottom">Likpakpaln word for rabbit or bunny or hare</note>, 
            <term xml:id="glossary4">nachiin</term><note type="footnote" n="2" place="bottom">Likpakpaln word for wolf</note>, and 
            <term xml:id="glossary6">unyii</term><note type="footnote" n="3" place="bottom">Likpakpaln word for crocodile</note>,” Bilinyi tells his audience, and proceeds thus:</p>
        <p>Once upon a time, nachiin went to the river to drink water but was prevented from doing so by unyii. 
            After much supplication, unyii finally allowed him to drink. When nachiin had had his fill, unyii then inquired from 
            him whether or not he could make her children’s skins as smooth and colorful as his. This pleased nachiin who is, as you 
            know, always hungry for meat; so he responded in the affirmative. But nachiin gave unyii one condition: on the day he would 
            transform the skins of her children into finer textures and colors, unyii would bring all her hatchlings to the riverbank 
            and retreat to the middle of the river. </p>
        <p>On the appointed day, unyii did as nachiin had instructed. When unyii was safely away in the middle of the river in her hole 
            of residence, nachiin made a fire, placed a basket nearby, and placed unyii’s hatchlings next to him. Now, nachiin had told 
            unyii that whenever she heard the sound, kpeeeeb, she should respond, “<term xm:id="glossary1">ami, ami, ami, ami, ami.</term>” As a result, whenever 
            nachiin placed one of unyii’s children on the burning coal to roast, the fat that dripped into the burning coal would produce 
            the sound, kpeeeeb – to which unyii would respond, “ami, ami, ami, ami, ami.” After roasting and eating one hatchling, nachiin 
            would take another, place it on the burning coal, and the dripping fat would produce the sound, kpeeeeb – to which unyii would 
            always respond, “ami, ami, ami, ami, ami.” Eventually, he finished eating all the hatchlings.</p>
        <p>When he was done, he gathered all the bones into a pile and hid them under the basket he had brought. He then instructed unyii 
            to wait for seven days before lifting the basket off her children. On that seventh day, he said, unyii would find her children 
            with transformed skins akin to his. Unyii obliged and waited. On the seventh day when unyii lifted the basket to look at her 
            children, she found only bones. </p>
        <p>Unyii became distraught and banned all animals from coming to drink water from the river.  Every animal that went to drink water 
            was turned away. When the situation became unbearable for sande, he hatched a plan to deceive unyii and drink water from the river.
            He went to the river and made an attempt to drink water, whereupon unyii pounced on him to tear him into shreds. But sande quickly 
            asked unyii to exercise patience and allow him to drink, after which he would capture and bring to her the creature that killed her 
            hatchlings.</p>
        <p>Unyii released sande and allowed him to drink the water. Having quenched his thirst, he then told unyii to smear her mouth with 
            <term xml:id="glossary7">tijun</term> and play dead on the sand on the riverbank. He added that while playing dead, unyii should open her mouth and allow houseflies to 
            hover around her mouth as though she were a carcass. He then arranged with unyii that he would deceive nachiin so that both him and 
            nachiin would put their testicles into unyii’s mouth: the small-sized testicles would obviously be his so unyii should not trap them 
            in her mouth; but the large-sized testicles would be nachiin’s so unyii should grab them and deal with nachiin.</p>
        <p>Having made this arrangement with unyii, sande ran off to get nachiin. On seeing him, he told nachiin he was returning from the river
             where he drank water to his fill and even bathed. He showed nachiin his wet body and deceived him that unyii was dead. Nachiin 
             then revealed to sande that he was the one who ate unyii’s hatchlings and that unyii obviously died out of grief. Sande quickly 
             called dibs on unyii’s carcass since he found it. Thereupon, nachiin retorted sharply:</p>
        <p>“<term xml:id="glossary2">Kinaatuuk kimina; naa sen m-mi m ti ŋmɔiŋ waabiyaab m ka u kpii? M-mi yi maa wan.</term>”   (The storyteller mimics nachiin as he renders this.)</p>
        <p>Sande replied, “How can it be yours when I was the one who found the carcass and informed you?”</p>
        <p>But nachiin maintained that since unyii died from the grief of the deaths of her hatchlings, and considering that he (nachiin) 
            was responsible for their deaths, he could certainly lay claim to unyii’s carcass. Sande then told nachiin that the claim to 
            unyii’s carcass should not be a bone of contention between them since they could easily settle it through a contest. He proposed 
            that to settle the issue, they would go to the riverside and each would place his testicles in unyii’s mouth. The one whose 
            testicles fit tightly into unyii’s mouth would be declared winner and receive unyii’s carcass as reward. To this, nachiin replied:</p>
        <p>“You idiot, how large-sized are your testicles? Let’s go.”</p>
        <p>On that note, the two set off for the riverside. When they got there, unyii was still lying on the riverbank in “play-dead” mode, 
            with mouth wide open and flies dancing all over it. Nachiin presumed she was really dead. Sande then said, “If unyii’s carcass is 
            mine, when I put my testicles in her mouth, may they fit tightly so that I can take her carcass home and eat. If not, then let my 
            testicles not fit.”</p>
        <p>“Well, how big are sande’s testicles?” Bilinyi asks rhetorically and proceeds:</p>
        <p>So when he put them in unyii’s mouth, they dangled in her mouth loosely. Nachiin immediately shoved sande aside and stepped forward. 
            Squatting over unyii, he pushed, and pushed, and pushed his testicles till they fit tightly into her mouth. (The storyteller squats 
            and demonstrates as he relates this.)</p>
        <p>He then turned to sande and said, “Hey idiot, as you can see, my testicles fit tightly so the carcass is mine.” Thereupon, unyii 
            grabbed nachiin’s testicles and wouldn’t let go. A struggle ensued. Try as nachiin might, he couldn’t break free from unyii’s grips.
             The struggle continued until unyii chewed off his testicles. Nachiin then ran off.</p>
        <p>By this time, sande had fled the scene and was hiding in an anthill. As fate would have it, when nachiin escaped from unyii’s grips, 
            he ran to that same anthill and sat on it. From the inside of the anthill, sande could see nachiin through a hole on top. He picked 
            a stick and poked nachiin’s fresh wound. Each time sande did this, nachiin would jump in pain and blame flies for the pain. But 
            sande’s luck soon ran out: when he was about to poke nachiin’s wound again, the latter caught sight of the stick and pulled it, 
            whereupon sande emerged hanging onto the stick. Sande took off running, nachiin pursued him, grabbed him, and threatened to eat him 
            since he was responsible for his predicament.</p>
        <p>Sande then offered to climb a nearby tree, collect firewood, and make a fire so that nachiin could roast him before eating. He argued 
            that his roasted meat would taste better than the raw one. Nachiin fell for it and asked him to climb the tree quickly and
             do as he had proposed. Sande climbed the tree, broke off one dry twig and sat motionless on the tree. Nachiin yelled at him to be 
             snappy and get down so that he would eat him. At that moment, sande suddenly responded, “whuoy!” – as though someone had called him. 
             Nachiin insulted him and told him to get busy instead of responding, “whuoy!” But sande replied that he was hearing voices and 
             that those voices were saying, “Here are footprints, the footprints; here are drops of blood.”</p>
        <p>“Here are footprints; here are drops of blood,” interjects one audience, who is probably wondering what that means. So the storyteller explains as follows:</p>
        <p>“That means here are nachiin’s footprints; here are drops of his blood. When nachiin lost his testicles and was running for his life, 
            he left behind a trail of drops of blood. So when he was being traced, wasn’t it natural that the search party would update one 
            another whenever they spotted his footprints and blood?”</p>
        <p>“They would,” agrees the audience.</p>
        <p>(Bilinyi then returns to his narration as follows:)</p>
        <p>So in reply to nachiin, sande said he had heard some people shouting that “here are footprints; here are drops of blood” and so that 
            was why he had responded whuoy!</p>
        <p>“Well, sit there unperturbed; they’re saying here are your footprints; here are drops of your blood,” sande told nachiin again.</p>
        <p>On hearing this, nachiin… (At this point, the storyteller breaks into laughter and gestures. So the audience who interjected earlier,
             fills in the gap amid laughter as well.)</p>
        <p>“He took off running. He ran and left sande,” she says.</p>
        <p>(Bilinyi resumes and completes the story thus:)</p>
        <p>Thanks to that, sande’s life was spared. This is why sande is wiser than nachiin. <term xml:id="glossary3">M muun ka maa tiin gur.</term></p>

        <head type="subTitle">A Glossary of Likpakpaln Words and Phrases</head>
        <list type="gloss">
            <label><hi rend="bold">ami:</hi></label>
            <item><gloss target="#glossary1">Likpakpaln equivalent of amen.</gloss></item>
            <label><hi rend="bold">kinaatuuk kimina; naa sen m-mi m ti ŋmɔiŋ waabiyaab m ka u kpii? M-mi yi maa wan:</hi></label>
            <item><gloss target="#glossary2">translated as, “You idiot; wasn’t I the one who ate her hatchlings and she died out of grief? Her carcass is mine.”</gloss></item>
            <label><hi rend="bold">m muun ka maa tiin gur:</hi></label>
            <item><gloss target="#glossary3">translated as “May I grow while my story diminishes. It is a shortened version of the standard conclusion, 
                “Maa tiin gur, ki gur, ki gur ki m muun, ki muun ke n-yaaja agbenja na” (transliterated as “May my story diminish and diminish and diminish 
                while I grow and grow as tall as my grandfather’s male Kapok tree”). This is one of the numerous ways in which a Konkomba storyteller can 
                end his/her story. This particular type of ending and its variants suggest that Konkombas believe that storytelling 
                (or entertainment in general) has health benefits, especially healthy physical growth. The association of storytelling with physical 
                growth is so entrenched in Konkomba belief system that it is even believed that when a child engages in storytelling at daytime – for 
                Konkomba storytelling sessions are held normally in the evenings after supper – he or she will have stunted growth.</gloss></item>
            <label><hi rend="bold">nachiin:</hi></label>
            <item><gloss target="#glossary4">Likpakpaln word for wolf. In Konkomba folklore, nachiin is the most unintelligent animal character. It almost 
                always falls prey to the antics of others, especially sande (i.e. rabbit).</gloss></item>
            <label><hi rend="bold">sande:</hi></label>
            <item><gloss target="#glossary5">Likpakpaln word for rabbit or bunny or hare. Sande is the wisest and trickster character in Konkomba folklore. 
                It is notorious for often using its cunning and witty nature to deceive other characters or wriggle its way out of difficult situations 
                – case in point, the story above.</gloss></item>
            <label><hi rend="bold">unyii:</hi></label>
            <item><gloss target="#glossary6">Likpakpaln word for crocodile. Unyii is sometimes euphemistically called ukpindaan (transliterated as 
                “the owner-of-the-river”) because Konkombas believe that it is the embodiment of the Konkomba river god/goddess. In the context 
                of this story, therefore, unyii’s refusal to allow the other animals to drink from the river, feeds into this Konkomba belief 
                – for unyii alone has the authority to determine who drinks from the river.</gloss></item>
            <label><hi rend="bold">tijun (aka tijon):</hi></label>
            <item><gloss target="#glossary7">variously known in West Africa as dawa dawa in Hausa, iru in Yoruba, colgo in Mooré, netetou in Wolof, etc., 
                tijun is a pungent condiment made from the beans of the African locust bean tree (aka Parkia biglobosa). It is usually prepared by women 
                by fermenting the boiled and pounded beans of Parkia biglobosa over several days. The end product has a pungent smell and is usually 
                molded into various shapes – mostly spherical and rectangular – and used to add flavor to various stews, soups, and dishes. Its pungent 
                smell is perhaps comparable to that of rotten cheese. Note that tijun can also be made from soybeans. </gloss></item>

            
        </list>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
