<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader> 
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt> 
                <title> 
                    Why Old People Have Grey Hair
                </title> 
                <author>Konkomba Oral Tradition (Ghana)</author>
                <storyteller> Naalabr </storyteller>
                <editor> Tasun Tidorchibe </editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <name> Tasun Tidorchibe </name>
                    <resp>transcript, editing and translation</resp>
                </respStmt>
                    <respStmt>
                    <name> Livia Heyer </name>
                    <name> Nadine Dorscheid </name>
                    <resp> coding and editing </resp>
                    </respStmt>
                <respStmt> 
                    <name> Dr. Eva Ulrike Pirker </name>
                    <resp> supervision </resp>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor type="digitisation"> E-Learning Förderfonds HHU </sponsor>
                <sponsor type="funding">Katholischer Akademischer Ausländerdienst</sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher> Centre for Translation Studies Düsseldorf </publisher>
                <status> not yet published</status> 
                <pubPlace> Düsseldorf </pubPlace>
                <address> <name type="institution"> Centre for Translation Studies Düsseldorf </name> 
                <name type="institution"> Heinrich-Heine-Universität Düsseldorf </name>
                <street> Universitätsstraße 1 </street>
                <postCode> 40225 </postCode>
                <name type="city"> Düsseldorf </name>
                <name type="country"> Germany </name>
                </address>
                <availability> not yet available </availability>
                <date> TBD </date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl> <title> Why Old People Have Grey Hair
              </title> <storyteller> Naalabr </storyteller> Translated by <editor role="translator"> Tasun Tidorchibe </editor> </bibl> 
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
            <encodingDesc>
                  <styleDefDecl scheme="css" Version="2​.1"/>
                  <tagsDesc>      
                  </tagsDesc>
                <editorialDecl> No author can be assigned to the story due to it being an oral tradition; The decision was taken to treat notes the same as a glossary in terms of coding</editorialDecl>
                <projectDesc>The project focuses on digitising oral folktales from Ghana, specifically the Konkomba people, through different media.
                  The project puts a body of oral folktales into writing and eventually makes them available as annotated, digitised narratives.
                  It thus aims to make a contribution to visibilising this culture, which through processes of colonisation, the accompanying priviledging of written/print culture and Eurocentric/Western thinking has been marginalised.</projectDesc>
                  </encodingDesc>
              <profileDesc> 
                  <creation> Originally told in
                  <place xml:id="Chakping, Ghana">
                       <placeName> Chakping, Ghana</placeName>
                       <location>
                           <geo> 9.67, -0.27 </geo>  
                       </location>    
                      </place>
                      transcribed folktale from Likpakpaln as told by <name type="storyteller"> Naalabr </name> on <date when="2022">16th March 2022 </date>in <name type="city">Chakping </name>, <name type="country">Ghana</name>
                    </creation>
                    <langUsage>
                        <language ident="lik">Likpakpaln</language>
                        <language ident="en">English</language>
                    </langUsage>
                    <textClass>placeholder tbd</textClass>
                </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text> 
        <body>
            <head type="mainTitle">Why Old People Have Grey Hair</head>
            <p>(as narrated by Naalabr in Chakping on 16/03/2022)</p>
            <div type="Introduction">
                <head type="subTitle">
                Introduction
                </head>
                <p>
                The following story, told by a child narrator, attempts to explain why people’s hair turn grey once they advance in age. According to the story, 
                a series of dumbfounding encounters between a man, his beans farm, his dog, and his ax on the one hand, and the man, an old woman, and a log on the other, 
                leads to unplanned sprint events that culminate in the old woman falling into ashes that turn her hair grey.
                </p>
                <p>
                    To watch the Likpakpaln narration <ref target="https://mediathek.hhu.de/watch/119761cf-45e0-44a3-bdf6-3f015c29099d">click here</ref>.
                </p>    
            </div>
            <div type="Story">
                <head type="subTitle">
                Story
                </head>
                <p>
                <q>My story is as follows…</q> Naalabr announces to his audience and proceeds thus:
                </p>
                <p>
                There lived a man who had a beans farm. After sowing the beans, he never visited the farm again. One day he decided to pay a visit to the farm. 
                To his pleasant surprise, when he got to the farm, he discovered that the beans had yielded. The man remarked that his beans had yielded beyond expectations. 
                On hearing this, the beans retorted: <q>What did you expect? That, we wouldn’t produce a high yield?</q>
                </p> 
                <p>
                Shocked, the man looked at his <term ref="#term2">ubɔja</term>, which only stared back at him in bewilderment. But for some strange reason, 
                the man got mad at the <term ref="#term2">ubɔja</term> for staring at him and tried to hit it with his <term ref="#term1">kichɔk</term>. 
                As he raised the <term ref="#term1">kichɔk</term>, the latter warned the man that it would have a bone to pick with him if <term ref="#term2">ubɔja</term> 
                bit it in retaliation. At that point, the man decided that he had heard enough so he took off running.
                </p>
                <p> 
                As he was running, he chanced upon an <term ref="#term3">upininkpil</term> who was carrying a log. <term ref="#term3">Upininkpil</term> called him 
                and asked why he was running as though something were in pursuit of him. In reply, the man told <term ref="#term3">upininkpil</term> that he cultivated 
                beans but failed to visit the farm till that day. On arrival at the farm, he discovered that the beans had yielded beyond his expectations so he made a remark 
                to that effect, whereupon the beans retorted: <q>What did you expect? That, we wouldn’t produce a high yield?</q> He added that his <term ref="#term2">ubɔja</term> 
                started staring at him so he got angry and wanted to hit it with his <term ref="#term1">kichɔk</term> but the <term ref="#term1">kichɔk</term> warned him that if 
                <term ref="#term2">ubɔja</term> bit it in retaliation, he would be held accountable.
                </p>
                <p>
                After listening to the man, <term ref="#term3">upininkpil</term> told him that was no justifiable reason to run. The log she was carrying then replied, 
                <q>If you were in his shoes, wouldn’t you have run?</q> On hearing this, <term ref="#term3">upininkpil</term> dropped the log and also took off running. 
                Unfortunately, while running, she fell into some ashes. Her hair consequently turned grey – and has been the case for all bipininkpiib since.
                </p>
                <p> 
                <q>So that’s why old people have grey hair,</q> one adult from the audience explains further amid laughter and chatter by the other audience.
                </p>
            </div>
            <div type="Glossary">
                <head type="subTitle">
                    A Glossary of Likpakpaln Words
                </head>
                <list type="gloss">
                
                    <label>kichɔk:</label>
                    <item>
                        <gloss xml:id="term1">
                            Likpakpaln word for an ax. It is typically small in nature. It is used for digging and chopping wood.
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <label>ubɔja:</label>
                    <item>
                        <gloss xml:id="term2">Likpakpaln word for a male dog. In everyday usage, ubɔja is sometimes inappropriately used for a dog – male or female – instead of the correct gender-neutral noun, 
                            ubɔ. In the context of this story, therefore, when the storyteller uses ubɔja, he is not referring to a male dog but a dog in general terms. So the dog in this story 
                            could be either male or female. FYI, a female dog is called ubɔsal in Likpakpaln.
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <label>upininkpil:</label>
                    <item>
                        <gloss xml:id="term3"> 
                            Likpakpaln word for an old lady or old woman. The plural form is bipininkpiib.
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                </list>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
